So we've taken a tour through a little
Bien, hemos hecho un recorrido
HelloWorldMongoDBStyle as well as Spark and Free Marker and
por "HelloWorldMongoDBStyle", Spark y Freemarker,
combining the three together into a single application.
combinando los tres en en una única aplicación.
Now, we get to go into a little bit more detail about
Ahora vamos a ver con un poco más de detalle cómo
using MongoDB from Java.
usar MongoDB desde Java.
So this is the example we had before HelloWorldMongoDBStyle
Éste es el ejemplo que teníamos antes, "HelloWorldMongoDBStyle",
where we created our MongoClient and got a database
donde creamos nuestro "MongoClient" y nos conectamos a una base de datos
from that client, the course database.
desde ese cliente, la base de datos "course".
And then, from that database we got a collection called
Luego, obtenemos una colección de esa base de datos llamada
hello and then, we retrieved one document from that
"hello" y, por último, recuperamos un documento de esa
collection and printed it out.
colección y lo imprimimos.
So we're going to take some of the scaffolding and do a
Vamos a tomar parte de este código como base para construir
simple application to insert a document into collections.
una aplicación simple que inserte un documento en una colección.
I'm going to create a new Java class called simple insert
Voy a crear una nueva clase Java llamada "SimpleInsertTest",
test, and I'll create my MongocClients.
y crearé mi "MongoClient".
And we'll just use the default here of local host 2717, and
Usaré aquí los valores por defecto, "localhost:27017",
add that host exception to my signature.
y añadiré a mi método la excepción "UnknownHostException".
And I don't need the database, so I'm just going to shorten
No necesito la base de datos, así que voy a simplificar esto,
this to just people collection equals clients dot get DB
"peopleCollection = client.getDB("course")
course dot get collection.
.getCollection("people");".
So if you recall, before HelloWorldMongoDBStyle, when
Si recuerdas de "HelloWorldMongoDBStyle",
we did a find one, the return value of find one
cuando hicimos un "findOne" el valor de retorno es de
is of type db object.
tipo "DBObject".
And db object is an interface.
Y "DBObject" es una interfaz.
So when we're inserting documents into a collection,
Cuando estamos insertando documentos en una colección,
we have to create the document first in order to insert it.
primero tenemos que crear el documento para poder insertarlo.
And we can't create an instance of an interface, so
Pero no podemos crear una instancia de una interfaz, por lo que
we need a concrete class that implements db object.
necesitamos una clase concreta que implemente "DBObject".
And the Mongo Java driver provides a class called
Y el driver de Mongo para Java proporciona una clase llamada
BasicDBObject, which implements DBObject.
"BasicDBObject", que implementa "DBObject".
And that's what we'll use when we're creating new documents
Ésa es la clase que usaremos para crear nuevos documentos e
to insert into the database.
insertarlos en la base de datos.
So we'll call it personDoc equals new basic DBObject.
Lo llamaremos "personDoc", "personDoc = new BasicDBObject()".
Let's create the simplest person doc that we can think
Vamos a crear la persona más simple que se nos ocurra,
of, which is id yeminj, and insert it.
por ejemplo "("_id", "yeminj")", y la insertamos.
And the way I insert it is I say, people collection because
La forma de hacerlo es a través del objeto "peopleCollection",
I want to insert it into the people
ya que quiero insertarlo en la colección
collection and I call insert.
"people", y llamo al método "insert",
And I pass a person doc.
pasándole "personDoc".
So what's interesting about this document is the field
Lo que resulta interesante de este documento es el nombre
name of the one field I created, which is id.
del campo que he creado, que es "_id".
So I set the id to be yeminj.
He asignado el valor "yeminj" a "_id".
And what's interesting about underscore id is that MongoDB
Y resulta interesante porque MongoDB requiere que cada
requires that every document in a collection has an
documento en una colección contenga un campo "_id",
underscore id field and that the value of
y el valor de dicho campo
that field is unique.
tiene que ser único.
So in this case, I'm creating an id field, and I'm sending
En este caso, estoy creando un campo "_id", y le estoy
it to yeminj.
dando el valor "yeminj".
And that means that no other documents in this collection
Eso significa que no habrá ningún otro documento en esta colección
can have the id of the string yeminj.
que pueda tener en el campo "_id" la cadena "yeminj".
And just so I can run this multiple times, I'm going to
Y como puedo ejecutar esto varias veces, voy a
call people at collection dot drop before I execute this.
llamar a "peopleCollection.drop()" antes de ejecutarlo.
And now, I think we're ready to run.
Ahora creo que estamos listos para ejecutarlo.
So I'll say run, and there's no output so it just exited.
Lo ejecutaré, y no imprime nada, simplemente termina.
So now, let's look at the collection.
Ahora echemos un vistazo a la colección.
So I'm going to say Mongo course.
Pondré "mongo course", de forma que la base de datos
So I default to the course database and show collections.
por defecto será "course", y "show collections".
And you can see now, there's a people collection that was
Y puedes ver que ahora tenemos una colección "people" que fue
created automatically when I inserted the first document to
creada automáticamente cuando inserté el primer documento en
that collection.
esa colección.
And let's see what's in the collection.
Veamos qué hay en la colección.
And you can see that there's a document id of yeminj.
Y puedes ver que hay un documento "".
So that's a basic insert of a document into collection.
Eso es una inserción básica de un documento en una colección,
But this is JSON, so let's make this document a little
pero esto es JSON, así que hagamos este documento un poco
more complex.
más complejo.
So I'm going to add a few more fields to this document.
Voy a añadir unos cuantos campos más al documento.
I'm going to say append, and I'll say name is Jeff Yemin
Voy a decir "personDoc .append("name", "Jeff Yemin")"
and append profession programmer.
".append("profession", "programmer");"
And let's run this again, and let's look again.
Ejecutémoslo otra vez y veamos qué pasa.
And I can see we have the same id, yeminj.
Y puedo ver que tenemos el mismo "'_id': 'yeminj'",
But now, we have name, Jeff Yemin, and profession,
pero ahora tenemos también "'name': 'Jeff Yemin'" y
programmer.
"'profession': 'programmer'".
So that shows how we can insert a document with
Esto demuestra cómo podemos insertar un documento con
multiple fields.
múltiples campos.
Now, let's use some of the power of JSON now to make a
Ahora, usaremos la potencia de JSON para hacer una
more complicated structure.
estructura más complicada.
So I'm going to also create a field for the list of
Voy a crear un campo para la lista de lenguajes
programming languages that I'm familiar with.
de programación que me resultan familiares.
So I'll say, person doc dot append languages.
Entonces diré, "personDoc. append("languages", )",
But in this case, I need a list not just a scalar value.
pero en este caso necesito una lista, no un valor escalar,
So I'm going to say, arrays dot as list.
por lo que pondré
And I'll say, Java c plus plus and, I don't know, XSLT.
"Arrays.asList("Java", "C++", "XLST")".
And we'll run it again, and print it again.
Lo ejecutaremos de nuevo, y veamos qué devuelve.
And now, we see that we have the three fields before, but
Ahora vemos que tenemos los tres campos de antes, pero
we also have a languages field.
también tenemos un campo "languages".
And you can see with these brackets that it's an array
Y puedes ver por estos corchetes que es un array
with three values, Java c plus plus and XSLT.
con tres valores, "Java", "C++" y "XLST".
Oh, I spelled XSLT wrong.
Oh, escribí mal "XSLT".
OK, let's show one last thing we can do with JSON.
Bien, veamos una última cosa que podemos hacer con JSON.
So I can also embed a nested document inside of the person.
También puedo embeber un documento dentro de la persona.
So I'm going to do that for my address.
Voy a hacer eso para mi dirección.
I'll create an address field and I'll say,
Crearé un campo "address" y pondré,
new basic db object.
"new BasicDBObject()",
So this is a nested document.
éste es mi documento anidado,
And I'll say, street Parkland.
y diré, "("street", "Parkland")".
Let's form it just a little differently.
Vamos a crearlo de manera ligeramente diferente.
Number is 20 and town is WayLand.
"("number", 20)" y "("town", "WayLand")".
Now, let's insert this document into the collection
Vamos a insertar este documento en la colección
and see what it looks like.
y veamos qué aspecto tiene.
So now, we have the same document, but we, in addition
Ahora tenemos el mismo documento pero, además de
to id, name, profession languages, we also have an
"_id", "name", "profession", "languages", también tenemos un
address field.
campo "address".
And this address field is a nested document with three
Y este campo "address" es un documento anidado con tres
fields, street, number, and town.
campos, "street", "number" y "town".